stclaircollege.ca 2018-06-13

# 2.16 Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act

                                                            POLICY AND PROCEDURE MANUAL
Policy Title:       FREEDOM OF INFORMATION AND                           Area of Responsibility:
                    PROTECTION OF PRIVACY ACT                            VICE PRESIDENT, COLLEGE
                                                                         COMMUNICATIONS AND COMMUNITY
Policy Section:     ADMINISTRATION                                       RELATIONS
Effective Date:     2016 02 18                                           Policy No: 2.16
Supersedes:         2014 09 02                                           Page: 1 of 16
2.16 Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act
Purpose:
To provide access to public information held by the College while protecting the privacy of personal
information in compliance with the Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (FIPPA).
Policy:
    1. The College will comply with FIPPA, which gives members of the general public a legal right to
         access certain information held by the College as an agency of the Government. FIPPA also
         gives individuals the right to access their own personal information and establishes standards to
         ensure that this information is protected.
    2. Access to Information
         2.1 Every person has the right to access a record or part of a record in the custody or under the
              control of the College unless the record or part of the record contains personal information or
              falls within one of the exemptions or exclusions listed below or provided for in FIPPA and
              the regulations.
         2.2 A person seeking access to a record shall:
              2.2.1    Make a request in writing to the Freedom of Information Officer
              2.2.2    Provide sufficient detail to identify the record; and
              2.2.3    Pay the prescribed fee.
         2.3 The College shall refuse to disclose personal information to any person other than the
              individual to whom the information relates except:
              2.3.1    Upon the prior written request or consent of the individual; subject to the exemptions
                       and exclusions set out in FIPPA;
              2.3.2    In compelling circumstances affecting the health or safety of an individual;
              2.3.3    In accordance with the provisions of the FIPPA and the regulations.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                         Page 2 of 16
      2.4 The College shall refuse to disclose a record:
          2.4.1   Where the disclosure could reasonably be expected to interfere with a law
                  enforcement matter;
          2.4.2   Where the disclosure could reasonably be expected to reveal information received in
                  confidence from another government body or its agencies;
          2.4.3   That reveals a trade secret or scientific, technical, commercial, financial, or labour
                  relations information belonging to a third party;
          2.4.4   That contains information relating to specific tests, testing procedures or techniques
                  that are used in the evaluation of students;
          2.4.5   That is subject to solicitor-client privilege; or
          2.4.6   In accordance with any of the other exemptions or exclusions in FIPPA.
   3. Collection, Use and Disclosure of Personal Information
      3.1 Personal information shall not be collected unless it is expressly authorized by statue, used
          for proposes of law enforcement, or necessary to the proper administration of a lawfully
          authorized activity.
      3.2 The College shall collect personal information necessary to accomplish the College’s
          academic and operational activities. The College collects and uses personal information for
          the following purposes:
          3.2.1   Recruitment, admission and registration, academic programs and evaluations,
                  graduation
          3.2.2   Review, evaluation and improvement of academic and non-academic programs
          3.2.3   Financial assistance and awards
          3.2.4   Alumni, development and marketing activities
          3.2.5   Institutional planning, research and statistics
          3.2.6   Reporting to government agencies and professional licensing bodies
          3.2.7   Employment related matters
          3.2.8   Safety and security
          3.2.9   Promotion in its print, electronic and internet publications
      3.3 In order to facilitate these purposes to develop, maintain and improve appropriate programs,
          policies and recruitment strategies, measure program performance, and evaluate future
          program needs, the College may aggregate or link personal information in different databases
          over which it has custody or control.
      3.4 The College remains accountable for personal information under its control, including
          personal information which is disclosed to third parties for processing. The College will use
          contractual or other means to protect personal information that has been transferred to service
          providers for processing.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                         Page 3 of 16
      3.5 Personal information collected by the College may be collected, used and/or disclosed in
          other jurisdictions for processing, including in some cases to service providers located in the
          United States of America.
      3.6 Personal information shall only be collected by the College directly from the individual to
          whom the information relates unless:
          3.6.1   The information is collected by a third party and disclosed to the College with the
                  consent of the individual if required and in accordance with that third party’s privacy
                  policies.
          3.6.2   The individual authorized another manner of collection
          3.6.3   The information is collected for the purpose of determining suitability for an honour
                  or award to recognize outstanding achievement or distinguished service;
          3.6.4   The information is collected for the purpose of the conduct of a proceeding or a
                  possible proceeding before a court or tribunal;
          3.6.5   The information is collected for the purpose of law enforcement; or
          3.6.6   Otherwise in accordance with provisions of FIPPA and the regulations.
      3.7 Where person information is collected, the College shall inform the individual to whom the
          information relates of the following:
          3.7.1   The legal authority for the collection;
          3.7.2   The principal purpose(s) for which the information is intended to be used; and
          3.7.3   The address and telephone number of an employee who can answer questions about
                  the collection.
          The College provides the information required by this section in a variety of ways, including
          through this policy, through Statements or notices posted on the College’s website, on
          application or other forms, or in the Student Handbook, “Just the Facts”.
      3.8 Individuals have a right to “opt out” or withdrawn consent to some or all uses and/or
          disclosures of their personal information. Depending on the use or disclosure in questions,
          opting out or withdrawing consent may impact the College’s ability to provide service to the
          individual, and may even prevent the individual from continuing as a student or employee of
          the College. The extent to which an opt-out request can be granted without impacting the
          College’s ability to provide services to the individual will be assessed on a case by case
          basis. Inquiries regarding opt-out and withdrawal of consent should be addressed to the FOI
          Officer.
      3.9 The College shall not use personal information in its custody or under its control except:
          3.9.1   Where the person to whom the information relates has identified that information in
                  particular and consented to its use;
          3.9.2   For the purpose for which is was obtained or complied or for a consistent purpose; or
          3.9.3   Otherwise in accordance with provisions of FIPPA and the regulations.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                         Page 4 of 16
      3.10    The College shall not disclose personal information in its custody or under its control
              except:
          3.10.1 As indicated in the “Just the Facts” Student Handbook, or for the safety and well-
                   being of the College and/or community or at the discretion of the College
          3.10.2 Where the person to whom the information relates has identified that information in
                   particular and consented to its disclosure;
          3.10.3 For the purpose for which it was obtained or complied or for a consistent purpose;
          3.10.4 Where the disclosure is made to a staff member, or consultant or agent engaged by
                   the College, who needs the record in the performance of his or her duties and where
                   disclosure is necessary and proper in the normal course of business;
          3.10.5 In compassionate circumstances to facilitate contact with the spouse, a close relative
                   or friend of an individual who is injured, ill or deceased; or
          3.10.6 Otherwise in accordance with provisions of FIPPA and the regulations
      3.11 FIPPA permits the disclosure of personal information to an institution or a law
          enforcement agency in Canada to help an investigation undertaken with a view to a law
          enforcement proceeding or from which a law enforcement proceeding is likely to result. Any
          requests by policy for information regarding students, faculty or staff are to be directed to the
          Freedom on Information & Privacy Protection Coordinator to determine what personal
          information can be released and maintain a record of the request.
      3.12 FIPPA shall not preclude the College from giving access to information in response to an
          oral request or in the absence of a request. Any existing practice for the release of
          information, which is not personal in nature, may continue at the discretion of the responsible
          Vice President.
      3.13 The College shall provide any person with a right of access upon request to his or her
          own personal information in the College’s possession, provided it can be described with
          sufficient specific information to make it reasonably retrievable by the College. The right to
          access is subject to the exemptions and exclusions prescribed in FIPPA and the regulations.
      3.14    Every individual who is given access to personal information is entitled to:
          3.14.1 Request correction of the personal information where the individual believes there is
                   an error or omission therein; and
          3.14.2 Require that a statement of disagreement be attached to the information reflecting
                   any correction that was requested but not made.
      3.15 All reasonable steps shall be taken to protect the security and confidentiality of personal
          information during its collection, storage, transportation, handling and destruction. All
          reasonable steps shall be taken to ensure that when personal information is to be destroyed, it
          is destroyed in such a way that it cannot be reconstructed or retrieved.
      3.16 Information collected or created by the College shall be maintained in accordance with
          legislative or other record retention requirements.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                         Page 5 of 16
      3.17 The College at its discretion may choose to destroy records it is no longer obliged to
          protect and retain.
      3.18 The College will provide information about its privacy policies and practices when and
          where appropriate, including by use of the Privacy Statement attached as Appendix 3.
   4. Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Coordinator
      4.1 Under FIPPA, the Chair of the Board of Governors, as designed head of the College, has
          power and duty to make decisions on requests to access College records. The Board of
          Governors shall delegate these powers and duties to an office of the College, the Vice
          President of College and Community Relations, who will act as the Freedom of Information
          and Protection of Privacy Coordinator (FOI Officer).
      4.2 The FOI Officer shall be responsible for the coordination of activities related to FIPPA.
      4.3 The FOI Officer shall be the contact person for all public inquiries regarding FIPPA.
          Transfers, severance and third party notification. The FOI Officer will rely on his/her
          knowledge of FIPPA and seek legal counsel if necessary to ensure that the College is in
          compliance with the legislation.
      4.4 Each area of the College shall name a Records Coordinator who will coordinate the search
          and the release of records to the FOI Officer, at his/her request. The areas of the College are:
              - President/Board of Governors
              - Academic Administration
              - Human Resources
              - Student Services
              - Strategic Planning
              - Advancement
              - Registrar’s Office
              - Finance and Facilities
              - Employment Centre
      4.5 The FOI Officer shall document information on all requests received, the rationale for
          decisions on access and the disposition of the requests. A tracking and recording system
          will be used to ensure that all requests are processed within the established time limits and to
          generate the statistics for the annual report to the Commissioner.
      4.6 The FOI Officer shall require the assistance of the President and Vice Presidents to monitor
          compliance with the FIPPA privacy provisions and the notification requirements in FIPPA
          and in this policy.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                       Page 6 of 16
Procedure
      Action                                                               Responsibility
1.    Receipt of Request
1.1   Submit written request to access information under FIPPA,            Requester
      including those from the Ministry or other government Agency
      to:      Freedom of Information Officer
               Vice President, College Communications and
               Community Relations
               2000 Talbot Rd., Windsor, Ontario N9A 6S4
               Telephone: 519-972-2762
1.2   With the written request, include sufficient details to identify the Requester
      record being sought and pay the prescribed fee of $5.00
1.3   Log the request from the date the College has received it            Assistant to FOI Officer
1.4   If the request is not clear and additional information is needed     FOI Officer
      within the thirty-day deadline, ask the requester for additional
      information to find the record. The time limit will be suspended
      until the FOI Coordinator received written notice of the additional
      information needed to continue with the search or to discontinue
      the search.
2.    Search for Record
2.1   With sufficient information to locate the record, forward the        FOI Officer
      request to the Records Coordinator for the Area concerned, along
      with time remaining to comply with the request.
2.2   When an Area receives a request:                                     Records Coordinator
           a. conduct a search for the requested record;
           b. determine whether the information requested can be
               retrieved in whole or in part;
           c. estimate the time and cost needed to search for, retrieve
               and prepare the information for release;
           d. forward the information with a recommendation for or
               against disclosure to the President or appropriate Vice
               President/Executive Director for his/her approval.
2.3    Review the request, the information retrieved and the               President or Vice Presidents
       recommendation for the release of the information
2.4   Provide the FOI Coordinator a written approval to release the        President or Vice Presidents
      information along with the information retrieved or a written
      refusal, along with reasons within the thirty-day deadline.
3.    Release of Information
3.1   If the search, preparation and photocopying of the records are       FOI Officer
      needed, notify the requester in writing advising of the fee
      estimate. If the fee estimate is over $100.00, a deposit equal to
      50% of the fee estimate will be required before processing the
      request. Upon completion of the request, inform the requestor of
      any additional amount outstanding. The records will not be
      released until payment has been received in full by the College.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                                                                   Page 7 of 16
3.2        If access to the records is to be provided, release the information                                    FOI Officer
           to the requestor within 30 calendar days after a ‘complete request’
           has been received by the College.
3.3        If access to the records is denied, within 30 calendar days after a                                    FOI Officer
           ‘complete request’ has been received by the College send a letter
           to the requester indicating the reason for refusal and his/her right
           of appeal to the Commissioner for review of the decision.
Related Materials
Office of the Information and Privacy Commission of Ontario. Procedures Manual
http://www.ipc.on.ca/english/Resources/IPC-Corporate/IPC-Corporate-Summary/?id-665
St. Clair College wishes to thank and acknowledge Algonquin College for their written permission to use their policies and procedures as precedents in the
preparation of St. Clair College’s policies and procedures.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                            Page 8 of 16
APPENDIX 1
SELECTED DEFINIATIONS FOR FIPPA
1. “Personal Information” means recorded information about an identifiable individual, including,
1) information relating to the race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation
   or marital or family status of the individual,
2) information relating to the education or the medical, psychiatric, psychological, criminal or
   employment history of the individual or information relating to financial transaction in which the
   individual has been involved,
3) any identifying number, symbol or other particular assigned to the individual,
4) the address, telephone number, fingerprints, or blood type of the individual,
5) the personal opinions or views of the individual except where they relate to another individual,
6) correspondence sent to an institution by the individual that is implicitly or explicitly of a private or
   confidential nature, and replies to that correspondence that would reveal the contents of the original
   correspondence,
7) the views or opinions of another individual about the individual, and,
8) the individual’s name where it appears with other personal information relating to the individual or
   where the disclosure of the name would reveal other personal information about the individual.
2. “Record” means any record of information however recorded, whether in printed form, on film, by
   electronic means or otherwise, and includes.
   a. correspondence, a memorandum, a book, a plan, a map, a drawing, a diagram, a pictorial or
       graphic work, a photograph, a film, a microfilm, a sound recording, a videotape, a machine
       readable record, any other documentary material, regardless of physical form or characteristics,
       and any copy thereof, and
   b. subject to the regulations, any record that is capable of being produced from a machine readable
       record under the control of an institution by means of computer hardware and software or any
       other information storage equipment and technical expertise normally used by the institutions;
       (“document”)

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                            Page 9 of 16
APPENDIX 2
FREEDOM OF INFORMATION AND PROTECTION OF PRIVACY ACT EXCERPTS
3. Obligation to disclose
   3.1. Despite any other provisions of this Act, a head shall, as soon as practicable, disclose any record
         to the public or persons affected if the head has reasonable and probable grounds to believe that
         it is in the public interest to do so and that the record reveals a grave environmental, health or
         safety hazard to the public. R.S.O. 1990, c. F. 31, s. 11 (1).
   3.2. Notice - Before disclosing a record under subsection (1), the head shall cause notice to be given
         to any person to whom the information in the record relates, if it is practicable to do so. R.S.O.
         1990, c. F. 31, s. 11(2).
   3.3. Contents of notice - The notice shall contain,
        a. a statement that the head intends to release a record or a part of a record that may affect the
             interests of the person;
        b. a description of the contents of the record or part that relate to the person; and
        c. a statement that if the person makes representations forthwith to the head as to why the
             record or part thereof should not be disclosed, those representations will be considered by the
             head. R.S.O. 1990, c. F.31, s. 11(3).
   3.4. Representations - A person who is given notice under subsection (2) may make representations
         forthwith to the head concerning why the record or part should not be disclosed. R.S.O. 1990, c.
         F.31, s. 11(4).
4. Personal Privacy
   4.1. A head shall refuse to disclose personal information to any person other than the individual to
         whom the information relates except,
        a. upon the prior written request or consent of the individual, if the record is one to which the
             individual is entitled to have access;
        b. in compelling circumstances affecting the health or safety of an individual, if upon disclosure
             notification thereof is mailed to the last known address of the individual to whom the
             information relates;
        c. personal information collected and maintained specifically for the purpose of creating a
             record available to the general public;
        d. under an Act of Ontario or Canada that expressly authorized the disclosure;
        e. for a research purpose if,
                      (i) the disclosure is consistent with the conditions or reasonable expectations of
                           disclosure under which the personal information was provided, collected or
                           obtained,
                      (ii) the research purpose for which the disclosure is to be make cannot be reasonably
                           accomplished unless the information is provided in individually identifiable form,
                           and

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                            Page 10 of 16
                     (iii) the person who is to receive the record has agreed to comply with the conditions
                           relating to security and confidentiality prescribed by the regulations; or
        f. if the disclosure does not constituted an unjustified invasion or personal privacy. R.S.O.
            1990, c. F.31, s. 21(1).
5. Use of Personal Information
   5.1. An Institution shall not use personal information in its custody or under its control except,
        a. where the person to whom the information relates has identified that information in particular
            and consented to its use;
        b. for the purpose for which it was obtained or compiled or for a consistent purpose;
        c. for a purpose for which the information may be disclosed to the institution under section 42
            or under section 32 of the Municipal Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act.
            R.S.O. 1990, c. F.31, s. 41.
        d. subject to subsection (2), an educational institution may use personal information in its
            alumni records for the purpose of its own fundraising activities, if the personal information is
            reasonably necessary for the fundraising activities.
   5.2. Notice on using personal information for fundraising - In order to use personal information in its
         alumni records for the purpose of its own fundraising activities, an educational institution shall,
         a. give notice to the individual to whom the personal information relates when the individual is
             first contacted for the purpose of soliciting funds for fundraising or his or her right to request
             that the information cease to be used for fundraising purposes;
         b. periodically and in the course of soliciting funds for fundraising, give notice to the
             individual to whom the personal information relates of his or her right to request that the
             information cease to be for fundraising purposes; and
         c. periodically and in a manner that is likely to come to the attention of individuals who may
             be solicited for fundraising, publish a notice of the individual’s right to request that the
             individual’s personal information cease to be used for fundraising purposes. 2005, c. 28,
             Sched. F. s. 5(2).
   5.3. Discontinuing use of personal information - An educational institution shall, when requested to
         do so by an individual, ceases to use the individual’s personal information under clause (1) (d).
         2005, c. 28, Sched. F, s. 5(2).
6. Where Disclosures is permitted
   6.1. An institution shall not disclose personal information in its custody or under its control except,
         a. in accordance with Part II;
         b. where the person to whom the information relates has identified that information in
             particular and consented to its disclosure;
         c. for the purpose for which it was obtained or complied or for a consistent purpose;
         d. where disclosure is made to an officer or employee of the institution who needs the record in
             the performance of his or her duties and where disclosure is necessary and proper in the
             discharge of the institutions functions;

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                        Page 11 of 16
      e. for the purpose of complying with an Act of Legislature or an Act of Parliament or a treaty,
          agreement or arrangement thereunder;
      f. where disclosure is by a law enforcement institution
              (i) to a law enforcement agency in a foreign country under an arrangement, a written
                   agreement or treaty or legislative authority, or
              (ii) to another law enforcement agency in Canada;
      g. where disclosure is to an institution or a law enforcement agency in Canada to aid an
          investigation undertaken with a view to a law enforcement proceeding or from which a law
          enforcement proceeding is likely to result;
      h. in compelling circumstances affecting the health or safety of an individual if upon disclosure
          notification thereof is mailed to the last known address of the individual to whom the
          information relates;
      i. in compassionate circumstances, to facilitate contact with a spouse, a close relative or a
          friend of an individual who is injured, ill or deceased;
      j. to a member of the Legislative Assembly who has been authorised by a constituent to whom
          the information relates to make an inquiry on the constituent’s behalf or, where the
          constituent is incapacitated, has been authorized by the spouse, a close relative or the legal
          representative of the constituent;
      k. to a member of the bargaining agent who has been authorized by an employee to whom the
          information relates to make an inquiry on the employee’s behalf or, where the employee is
          incapacitated, has been authorized by the spouse, a close relative or the legal representative
          of the employee;
      l. to the responsible minister;
      m. to the Information and Privacy Commissioner;
      n. to the Government of Canada in order to facilitate the auditing of shared cost programs; and
      o. subject to subsection (2), an educational institution may disclose personal information in its
          alumni records for the purpose of its own fundraising activities if,
                   (i) the educational institution and the person for whom the information is disclosed
                        have entered into a written agreement that satisfies the requirements of subsection
                        (3), and
                   (ii) the personal information is reasonably necessary for the fundraising activities.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                         Page 12 of 16
APPENDIX 3
St. Clair College Privacy Statement
St. Clair College (the “College”) is committed to protecting the privacy of your personal information.
The College at all times collects, uses and discloses personal information in accordance with the
Freedom of Information and Personal Privacy Act, R.S.O. 1990, c. F.31 (“FIPPA”), and under
authority of the Ontario Colleges of Applied Arts and Technology Act, 2002, S.O. 2002, c. 8, Sched. F,
and other relevant legislation. The College’s personal information handling practices are set out in more
detail in its Policy 7.2: Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy.
The College is required to report student-level enrolment-related data to the Ministry of Training,
Colleges and Universities under the authority of the Ontario Colleges of Applied Arts and Technology
Act, 2002, S.O. 2002, Chapter 8, Schedule F, and Section 6. The Ministry collects this data, which
included limited personal information such as Ontario Education Numbers, student characteristics and
educational outcomes, in order to administer government postsecondary funding, policies and programs,
including planning, evaluation and monitoring activities. Information collected by the College is used
for educational, administrative and statistical purposes of the College and/or ministries and agencies of
the Government of Ontario and the Government of Canada.
Further information on the collection and use of student-level enrolment-related data can be obtained
from the Government of Ontario or Ministry of Training Colleges and Universities websites or by
writing to the Director, Postsecondary Finance Branch, Postsecondary Education Division, 7th Floor,
Mowat Block, 900 Bay Street, Toronto, ON M7A 1L2.
The College collects personal information at several points of contact. It collects personal information
from prospective students during marketing and recruitment campaigns, and during the application
process. It collects personal information from current students at various times and in various ways
throughout their tenure with the College. It may collect personal information form alumni after their
tenure at the College. It collects personal information from staff at various times and in various ways in
the course of the employment relationship.
Personal Information is collected and used for a number of reasons. In the case of prospective students,
information is collected and used primarily for the purpose of making admissions-related decision,
including initial contact with the students, the creation, processing and maintenance of student
applications, acceptance and registration with the College. In the case of students whose applications are
accepted, and current students of the College, information collected before or after enrolment is also
collected for the purposes of administering the student’s studies at the College, and to assist the College
in providing academic and other services to the student. Information collected from prospective or
current students before or after enrolment may also be used for the purposes of statistical analysis,
research and marketing. It may also be aggregated, linked to other data, or otherwise used by the
College for the purposes of reviewing, improving and developing College programs, policies, and
recruitment strategies, measuring program performance and assessing future program needs. In the case
of College staff, information is collected primarily for the purpose of managing the employment
relationship.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                         Page 13 of 16
Personal information may also be used or disclosed for purposes reasonably consistent with these
purposes. Specific purposes for the collection of information will be set out at the time of collection
where required and where distinct from the above. If no purpose is indicated, the information is
collected and will be used for the above purposes, or purposes reasonably consistent with those set out
above, subject to the provision of FIPPA.
The College will use or disclose personal information where reasonably necessary to achieve the
purposes for which it was collected, or where authorized or required by law to do so. The College may
also make available personal information, as required, to third parties who provide services reasonably
necessary to the College’s operations, or to the achievement of the purposes stated above. On occasions,
personal information may be collected, uses and/or disclosed in jurisdictions outside of Ontario.
Personal information in different databases in the custody or control of the College may also be linked or
aggregated in order to achieve the purposes set out above.
By providing your personal information to the College, you consent to the use of disclosure of personal
information as set out above and to the extent necessary to fulfil these purposes. You have a right to
withdraw your consent to the use or disclosure of your personal information; however this may have an
impact on the College’s ability to provide services to you, including in the case of current students your
ability to continue in your studies at the College. Students wishing to withdraw consent in full or in part
to the use or disclosure of their personal information should contact the FOI Officer for more
information on the consequences of withdrawing consent.
The College will take all reasonable measures to safeguard personal information in its control, including
but not limited to physical, technical, and operational measures. The College will require, by contract or
otherwise, that any third party service provider to whom personal information is transferred has adequate
policies and safeguards in place to protect that information. The College will ensure that information
which is disposed of in accordance with College policies and all applicable regulations is destroyed
securely and in a manner which protects the privacy of the information holder.
You have a right of access to your personal information in the control of the College, subject of the
terms of FIPPA and its regulations. To make such a request, or if you have questions about this
Statement or about the College’s personal information practices please contact:
         Freedom of Information Officer
         2000 Talbot Rd.
         Windsor, ON N9A 6S4
         Telephone: 519-972-2727 ext. 2762
If you have a complaint about the College’s handling of your personal information, please contact the
FOI Coordinator. If your complaint is not resolved to your satisfaction, FIPPA provides a mechanism
for independent review by contacting the Information and Privacy Commissioner of Ontario.

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                       Page 14 of 16
                                        EXHIBIT A (For Students)
CONSENT TO OBTAIN, RELEASE AND/OR EXCHANGE INFORMATION
Privacy of Records - A student has a right to the privacy of his/her academic, non-academic and
disciplinary records and the right personally to examine such records, from time to time, including
the right to challenge the accuracy or presence of any entry on his/her records and the right to be
notified, in writing, in the event of adverse information being placed in his/her official file.
Release of Information - A student has a right to expect that personal information will not be
released to anyone, without the prior written consent of the individual concerned and that any
disclosure will comply with the appropriate provisions of the Freedom of Information and Protection
of Privacy Act, R.S.O. 1990 (Section 41 & 42). Grades/evaluation will not be posted by name and
will not be given to others (excluding the Registrar’s Office) without the individual’s written
permission.
        DATE: _________________________________________________
        TO:     _________________________________________________
                _________________________________________________
        I,      _________________________________________________
                          PRINT NAME
(in accordance with the Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act, R.S.O. 1990), hereby
authorize St. Clair College to obtain, release and/or exchange information with the above named
agent(s) or agency(ies) regarding my grades, attendance and any other appropriate information
relating to my schooling at St. Clair College which may be legitimately required.
I may revoke this permission for the release of my personal information about my schooling at St.
Clair College at any time by notifying, in writing, the Freedom of Information Coordinator at St.
Clair College.
______________________________                         ______________________
Signature of Student                                   Date
*********************************************************************************
REVOCATION OF PERMISSION FOR THE RELEASE OF STUDENT INFORMAITON
I do hereby revoke permission for the release of information about my schooling at St. Clair College.
______________________________                         ______________________
Signature of Student                                   Date

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                   Page 15 of 16
                                        EXHIBIT B (for Staff)
CONSENT TO OBTAIN, RELEASE AND/OR EXCHANGE INFORMATION
Privacy of Records - A staff member has a right to the privacy of his/her records and the right
personally to examine such records, from time to time, including the right to challenge the accuracy
or presence of any entry on his/her records and the right to be notified, in writing, in the event of
adverse information being placed in his/her official file.
Release of Information - A staff member has a right to expect that personal information will not be
released to anyone, without the prior written consent of the individual concerned and that any
disclosure will comply with the appropriate provisions of the Freedom of Information and Protection
of Privacy Act, R.S.O. 1990. Personal information will not be given to others without the individual’s
written permission.
        DATE: _________________________________________________
        TO:    _________________________________________________
               _________________________________________________
        I,     _________________________________________________
                       PRINT NAME
(in accordance with the Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act, 1990), hereby
authorize St. Clair College to obtain, release and/or exchange information with the above named
agent(s) or agency(ies) regarding my grades, attendance and any other appropriate information
relating to my schooling at St. Clair College which may be legitimately required.
This permission for the release of my personal information by St. Clair College, may be revoked by
me at any time by notifying, in writing, the Freedom of Information Coordinator at St. Clair College.
______________________________                        ______________________
Signature of Staff Member                             Date
REVOCATION OF PERMISSION FOR THE RELEASE OF STAFF INFORMAITON
I do hereby revoke permission for the release of information about me by at St. Clair College.
______________________________                        ______________________
Signature of Staff Member                             Date

Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy                                                                                 Page 16 of 16
                                                                                                                                        EXHIBIT C
                                                                                                 Access/Correction Request
                                                                               Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy
 Requester (Please Print)
 Last Name                                        First Name                           Middle Name                                      Mr.    Mrs.
                                                                                                                                        Ms.    Miss
 Address (Street/Apt. No./P/O. Box No./R.R. No.)                                       City or Town                   Province
 Postal Code           Telephone Number(s)        Area Code                                                              Area Code
                               Day                                                                Evening      
 Name of Institution/Organization (if applicable):
 Request For
  Access to General           Access to Own Personal          Correction to Own Personal         Access to Third Party Information
    Records                     Records                          Records                             Waiver/Consent Attached:                        Yes
 Name of Institution request made to:
 If request is for access to, or correction of personal information records:
             Last name appearing on records:                                       same as above        or    
 Description of Request
 Detailed description of requested records, personal information records, third party records or personal information to be corrected.
 (a. If you are requesting access to, or correction of, your personal information, please identify the personal information bank or record containing
       the personal information, if known.
   b. If you are requesting access to third party information, the request must be accompanied by a signed waiver/consent form.
   c. If you are requesting a correction of personal information, please indicate the desired correction and, if appropriate, attach any supporting
       documentation. You will be notified if the correction is not made and you may require that a statement of disagreement be attached to your
       personal information.)
 Preferred method of access to records                     Signature                                           Date
  Examine Original
  Receive Copy                                                                                                      Day               Month        Year
 For Institutional Use Only
 Date received                                            Request Number                                       Comments
       Day              Month               Year
Personal information contained on this form is collected pursuant to Freedom of information and Protection of Privacy legislation and will be used for
the purpose of responding to your request. Questions about this collection should be directed to the Freedom of Information and Privacy Coordinator.
